Finding Aid for President (University of Michigan) records, 1967-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- President's Supplemental Files 1967/68-2006/07
  - Lee C. Bollinger 1997-2002
    - Life Sciences Commission 1998-2000
      - Meetings
        - Life Science Commission Minutes 1998 (Box 354)
        - Life Science Advisory Committee (LSAC) 1999-2000 (Box 354)
      - Rankings (Box 354)
      - Reports
        - Final: Challenges and Opportunities in Understanding the Complexity of Living Systems February 10, 1999 (Box 354)
        - Draft February 1, 1999 (Box 354)
        - Commission Documents (Numbers 1 and 2) (Box 354)
        - Report Prep 1998 (Box 354)
      - Signatures (Box 354)
      - Subcommittees 1998 (Box 354)
      - Survey Responses 1998, 2 folders (Box 354)
    - Life Science Initiative (LSI) 1999-2001
      The Life Sciences Initiative (LSI) sub-subseries, 1999-2001 (1.0 linear feet), consists of materials on the development and implementation of a strategy to make the University of Michigan a leader in life sciences research. At the turn of the 21st century, huge progress was being made in life sciences in universities throughout the country and the world. President Bollinger was deeply interested in moving the University of Michigan forward in this field. The efforts made through the Life Sciences Initiative led to several new developments including the building of the Life Sciences Institute between central campus and the medical campus. Most of the files in this sub-subseries are background and planning materials. Researchers should also refer to the Life Sciences folders in the Topical Files series for additional information.
      - Index to LSI Files (Box 434)
      - Background Information
        - Faculty Comments (Box 434)
        - National View (Box 434)
        - Princeton University Schultz Lab (Box 434)
        - Regents Action Request May 1999 (Box 434)
        - Regents Item -- Palmer Drive June 1997 (Box 434)
        - Regents Presentations April 1999 (Box 434)
        - University of California, San Francisco -- Mission Bay (Box 434)
        - University of Pennsylvania Clinical Research Building (Box 434)
        - University of Wisconsin Biochemistry Building (Box 434)
      - Communications -- External
        - Background of Life Sciences Commission (Box 434)
        - Initiative Communications (Box 434)
        - President's Message May 1999 May 2000 (Box 434)
        - Life Sciences Inquiries (Box 434)
        - Letters from UM Officials and Others (Box 434)
      - Communications -- Internal (Box 434)
      - By-Laws (Box 434)
      - Charge to Faculty Advisory Committee (Box 434)
      - Progress and Planning Report (Box 434)
      - LSI Briefing (Box 434)
      - Presentations (Box 435)
      - Articles (Box 435)
      - Reports
        - LSI and the Institute for the Study of Biological Complexity and Human Values
          - May 1999 (Box 435)
          - June 1999 (Box 435)
        - Life Sciences Institute July 1999 (Box 435)
        - Challenges and Opportunities in Understanding the Complexity of Living Systems February 10, 1999 (Box 435)
      - LSI Notes (Box 435)
      - Budget (Box 435)
      - External Advisors, Hosting Expenses (Box 435)
      - Public Relations for Donors (Box 435)
      - Technology Management (Box 435)
    - President's Information Revolution Commission (PIRC) 2000-2001
      The President's Information Revolution Commission (PIRC) sub-subseries, 2000-2001 (1.5 linear feet), includes files on a commission formed under the direction of President Bollinger to investigate how the University of Michigan community was thinking about, discussing, and using information technology. Another exciting feature of the late 20th and early 21st centuries was the rapid development of new information technology, and Bollinger was interested in keeping the University engaged in the new developments. The PIRC was charged with thinking about how the University could take advantage of the progress in information technology, and become a leader in using information technology in the classroom, both onsite, and for distance learning purposes. The files in this sub-subseries contain background materials, minutes, correspondence, reports, and files from the various sub-commissions within the PIRC.
      - General Files
        - Administration /Background
          - General (Box 435)
          - Charge to the Commission (Box 435)
        - Budget (Box 435)
        - Correspondence (Box 435)
        - Implementation (Box 435)
        - Materials Distributed (Box 435)
        - Minutes /Notes (Box 435)
        - Newspaper Articles (Box 435)
        - Reference Materials, 3 folders (Box 435)
        - Reports, 2 folders (Box 435)
        - Retreat February 10, 2001 (Box 436)
        - Surveys /Forums
          - PIRC Co-Sponsored Forums
            - John Seely Brown Symposium (Box 436)
            - Law, Policy, and the Convergence of Telecommunications and Computing Technology (Box 436)
            - Social Sciences and the Internet (Box 436)
            - Virtual Universities (Box 436)
          - WSWT /HSWT Forum, October 10 and 16 2001 (Box 436)
      - Subcommissions
        - eC2 Subcommission on e-Outreach
          - General, 2 folders (Box 436)
          - Draft Reports (Box 436)
          - Articles (Box 436)
          - Meeting Minutes (Box 436)
          - Meeting Grids (Box 436)
        - How Should We Teach (HSWT)
          - General (Box 436)
          - Draft Reports (Box 436)
          - Meeting Minutes (Box 436)
          - E-mails (Box 436)
        - IT Infrastructure
          - General (Box 436)
          - Draft Reports (Box 436)
          - Other Relative Reports (Box 436)
          - Meeting Minutes (Box 436)
          - E-mails (Box 436)
        - Research (Box 437)
          - General (Box 437)
          - Draft Reports (Box 437)
          - Meeting Minutes (Box 437)
          - E-mails (Box 437)
          - Pertinent Articles (Box 437)
        - What Should We Teach (WSWT)
          - Relative Reports to Draft Reports (Box 437)
          - Meeting Minutes (Box 437)
          - E-mails (Box 437)
        - WSWT /HSWT Joint Subcommission
          - General, 3 folders (Box 437)
          - Draft Reports (Box 437)
          - Meeting Minutes (Box 437)
          - E-mails (Box 437)
          - Pertinent Articles (Box 437)
    - Universitas 21 (U21) 1998-2002
      The Universitas 21 sub-subseries, 1998-2002 (1.5 linear feet) consists of administrative materials, correspondence, minutes, brochures, progress reports, background materials, and articles on the Universitas 21 consortium. Universitas 21 is an international consortium of 21 leading research universities. The purpose of the consortium is to advance international higher education through collaboration between the member institutions, as well as helping to promote the missions of each respective institution. The University of Michigan joined Universitas 21 in 1999 and was a member institution for several years.
      - Index to Universitas 21 Files (Box 437)
      - Administration
        - Structure Paper 1998 (Box 437)
        - Overview (Box 437)
        - U21 Executive Committee (Box 437)
        - U21 Fellows (Box 437)
        - U21 Contact Officers (Box 437)
      - Articles of Association
        - U21 Articles -- Signed (Box 437)
        - U21 Articles -- General (Box 437)
        - Association Protocols (Box 437)
      - Fees and Payments (Box 437)
      - Benchmarking (Box 437)
      - Brochure (Box 437)
      - Collaborations (Box 437)
      - Correspondence (Box 437)
      - Minutes /Notes
        - Contact Officers Meeting Minutes (Box 437)
        - Annual Meeting Minutes (Box 437)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 437)
        - First Faculties of Education Meeting September 26-28, 2000 (Box 437)
      - E-Education Project (Box 437)
      - U21 Global, 2 folders (Box 437)
      - Project 2000 (Box 438)
        - U21 Global Update March 18, 2002 (Box 438)
        - E-Education Project 2000 January 10, 2001 (Box 438)
        - U21 Global Joint Venture Business Plan December 15, 2000, 2 folders (Box 438)
        - The Story of the Thompson Corporation (P.R. Materials) (Box 438)
        - U21 Global Meeting January 29-30, 2001 (Box 438)
      - Student Exchange (Box 438)
      - Scholars Program (Box 438)
      - Fellowships (Box 438)
      - Newsletters and Progress Reports (Box 438)
      - Newspaper Articles (Box 438)
      - U21 Projects -- Global Education Presentations (Box 438)
      - Participating Universities, 8 folders (Box 438)
      - Visitors
        - General (Box 438)
        - University of New South Wales August 1998 (Box 438)
        - Dean Clair Chilvers, University of Nottingham September 1998 (Box 438)
        - Singapore Delegation September 1999 (Box 438)
        - University of Otago November 1999 (Box 438)
        - Bertram Frost, University of Queensland January 2000 (Box 438)
      - Student Organizations (Box 438)
      - Web Site (Box 438)
      - U21 Global Withdrawal (Box 438)
    - Correspondence 1887-2001
      The Correspondence sub-subseries, 1997-2001 (3 linear feet) is largely made up of correspondence written to Bollinger, which can be found in the Alphabetical files. This group of correspondence is organized alphabetically according to the last name or corporate name of the author. Also included are copies of mass mailings sent out from the president's office, and staff letters composed by staff in the president's office on behalf of the president.
      - Alphabetical Files 1997-2001 (Box 439)
        - A -- G, 11 folders (Box 439)
        - H -- Ri, 16 folders (Box 440)
        - Rj -- Z, 12 folders (Box 441)
      - Mass Mailings 1997-2002, 3 folders (Box 441)
      - Memos 1997-2001 (Box 441)
      - Staff Letters 1997-2001 (written by president's office staff on behalf of the president) (Box 441)
    - Admissions Lawsuits
      The Admissions Lawsuits sub sub-series consists primarily of court filings and correspondence, including support and criticism of the university's position and interaction with the General Counsel's office, filed in chronological order and relating to the court cases Gratz v. Bollinger and Grutter v. Bollinger, which challenged undergraduate and Law School affirmative action admissions policies, respectively. While most of the content is from the Bollinger era, some of the documents date from the White and Coleman administrations. This sub sub-series contains attorney-client privileged documents and is closed under the client/patient records restriction. For more materials related to these admissions cases, please see the University of Michigan Admissions Lawsuits collection.
      - September 1999-2004, 20 folders (Box 518)
      - 1997-August 1999, 20 folders (Box 519)
    - Campus Plan
      The Campus Plan sub sub-series continues from earlier accessions and consists of correspondence and background information including materials on other Venturi, Scott Brown and Associates projects, a report on the history of the President's House, plans for a renovation and expansion of Hill Auditorium by Albert Kahn Associates, and a feasibility study for a Crossroads Center.
      - Background Information (Box 487)
        - General, 1997-2001 (Box 487)
        - The CrossRoads: A Building for the 21st Century-Final Feasibility Study, 1998 (Box 487)
        - Hill Auditorium Renovation and Expansion, 1999 (Box 487)
        - A History of the President's House at the University of Michigan, 1999 (Box 487)
        - Venturi, Scott Brown and Associates (VSBA), 1999-2002 (Box 487)
      - Correspondence, 1998-2002, 3 folders (Box 487)
    - Correspondence
      The Correspondence sub sub-series continues from earlier accessions and contains content relating to the Code of Student Conduct and university commissions such as the University Investment Commission, Commission on the Undergraduate Experience, and President's Information Revolution Commission. This sub sub-series also contains requests for funding, information, recognition, etc.
      - Requests, 1997-2000, 3 folders (Box 487)
      - Student Code, 1997-1999 (Box 487)
      - University Commissions, 2000-2002 (Box 487)
    - Events
      The Events sub sub-series continues from earlier accessions and consists of an appointment book listing the various events Bollinger was scheduled to attend in 2001.
      - Appointment Book, 2001 (Box 487)
    - Life Sciences Initiative
      The Life Sciences Initiative (LSI) sub sub-series continues from earlier accessions and consists of materials relating to the Michigan Life Sciences Corridor, which was created in 1999 to invest in biotech research at the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, Wayne State University, and the Van Andel Institute. Included in this sub sub-series is the Battelle Report about prospects for life sciences industry development in Michigan.
      - Michigan Life Sciences Corridor, 2000-2001, 3 folders (Box 487)
  - B. Joseph White
    The B. Joseph White sub-series includes one sub sub-series: Correspondence. The files contain alphabetically-arranged outgoing correspondence from White's tenure as interim president from January through July 2002.
    - Correspondence
      - A-Z, 2002, 26 folders (Box 488)
      - Group Memos, 2002 (Box 488)
  - Mary Sue Coleman 2001-2008
    The Mary Sue Coleman subseries included three sub-subseries: Events; Executive Officers Meetings; and Reports.
    - Events
      The Events sub-subseries, 2001-2008 (0.8 linear feet), includes files on several events including Salk Vaccine 50th Anniversary, online, the March 2003 Royal Shakespeare Company residency, a visit by the Dalai Lama, and perhaps most notable, September 11, 2001. The national tragedy involved airplanes crashing into the World Trade Center in New York, the Pentagon in Washington D.C., and in a field in Pennsylvania, was deeply devastating to the University of Michigan community. Students, faculty, and staff were affected by the tragedy, and eighteen alumni lost their lives in the attacks. The files contain materials on the university's response to the attacks, including the establishment of a scholarship fund for children of the alumni killed in the attacks that would be available if they chose to attend the University of Michigan.
      - Dalai Lama Visit April 2008 (Box 442)
      - Royal Shakespeare Company (RSC) 2001-2003
        - March 2003 Residency
          - General (Box 442)
          - RSC Board of Governors (Box 442)
      - Salk Vaccine 50th Anniversary, 2005
        [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2031
        - Panel Discussion, .ZIP and .MP4 files
        - Last Mile, .ZIP and .MP4 files
      - September 11, 2001 (9/11)
        - General 2001-2002 (Box 442)
        - Memorial Plaque 2002 (Box 442)
        - Memorial Scholarship
          - General 2002, 2005 (includes a CD-R containing documents related to the scholarship), 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 442)
          - Recipients 2002 (Box 442)
      - "A View From the Bridge" (event honoring Arthur Miller and William Bolcom) December 2002 (Box 442)
      - President's House Guest Book 1981-2004 (Volume 1)
    - Executive Officers Meetings
      The Executive Officers Meetings sub-subseries, 2004-2005 (0.5 linear feet), is fairly straight forward, containing agendas, minutes, background materials, and correspondence from meetings dating from September 2004 to July 2005.
      - 2004
        - September -- December, 18 folders (Box 442)
      - 2005 (Box 443)
        - January -- July, 31 folders (Box 443)
    - Reports
      The Reports sub-subseries, 2005 (1 linear foot and 0.72 GBs) consists entirely of reports from the Accreditation Board for Engineering Technology's (ABET) visit to the College of Engineering in 2005. Included are the College of Engineering's Institutional Profile, and self study reports from the departments within the College of Engineering. The reports provide a comprehensive picture of the state of the College of Engineering at the time of the ABET accreditation visit, as well as responses to the House Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Courts, the Internet and Intellectual Property Survey of Network and Data Integrity Practices, online.
      - Engineering, College of (Box 444)
        - Accreditation Board for Engineering Technology (ABET) Accreditation Visit 2005
          - Institutional Profile (Box 444)
          - Self-Study Reports
            - Aerospace Engineering (Box 444)
            - Biomedical Engineering (Box 444)
            - Chemical Engineering (Box 444)
            - Civil Engineering (Box 444)
            - Computer Engineering (Box 444)
            - Electrical Engineering (Box 444)
            - Industrial and Operations Engineering (Box 444)
            - Materials Science and Engineering (Box 444)
            - Mechanical Engineering (Box 444)
            - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering (Box 444)
            - Nuclear Engineering and Radiological Sciences (Box 444)
      - Responses to House Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Courts, the Internet and Intellectual Property Survey of Network and Data Integrity Practices, ca. 2007, .MOV and .JPG files
    - President’s China Task Force 2007-2008
      The President's China Task Force (CTF), chaired by Gary Krenz (Special Counsel to the President) was charged with examining the university's relationship with Chinese educational institutions and government agencies and exploring opportunities for collaboration in the future. The task force records consist of a C-Tools site with digital files (pdf, and doc) including a CTF overview and charge, meeting agendas and minutes, proposals and reports.
      - C-Tools Site
    - Athletics
      The Athletics sub sub-series consists primarily of reports documenting Michigan's involvement as a member institution of both the Big Ten Conference and National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA). During the early years of the Coleman administration, one of the major issues confronting Michigan athletics was penalties imposed by the NCAA for infractions committed within the basketball program. Documents reflecting the NCAA's sanctions and the university's response include a copy of the university's appeal to the Division I Committee on Infractions Report No. 208 and attachments from a compliance progress report submitted to the NCAA.
      - Amaker, Tommy, 2003 (Box 488)
      - Appeal of the University of Michigan of Portions of the Report of the NCAA Division I Committee on Infractions, 2003, 2 folders (Box 488)
      - Big Ten Conference
        - Basketball Ticket Sales and Financial Settlement Reports, 2006 (Box 488)
        - Council of Presidents/Chancellors Meeting Materials, 2001 (Box 488)
        - Media Agreements Reference Manual, 2007 (Box 488)
      - Compliance Progress Report Attachments 73-130, 2005, 3 folders (Box 488)
      - Football Eligibility, 2004 (Box 517)
      - National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA)
        - General, 2003-2004, 3 folders (Box 517)
        - Certification (Steering Committee Materials), 2003 (Box 489)
    - Boards/Committees
      The Boards/Committees sub sub-series consists primarily of board books from boards and committees on which Coleman served. Materials in this sub sub-series include minutes, agendas, reports, resolutions, presentation slide printouts, copies of correspondence, and financial statements. While some groups are university-related, such as the Investment Advisory Committee and Sustainability Executive Council, most are organizations dedicated to revitalizing the state. These latter include Business Leaders for Michigan, Detroit Renaissance, and the Strategic Economic Investment and Commercialization Board.
      - Business Leaders for Michigan
        - Board of Directors
          - Resource Book, 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 489)
          - Retreats, 2010-2011, 4 folders (Box 489)
        - Economic Competitiveness Benchmarking Report, 2011 (Box 489)
        - Executive Committee, 2009-2011, 7 folders (Box 489)
        - Michigan Turnaround Plan, 2010 (Box 489)
        - Road to Renaissance: Final Business Plans, 2007 (Box 489)
      - Detroit Renaissance
        - Board of Directors
          - Information Manual, 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 489)
          - Meetings, 2006-2007, 4 folders (Box 489)
          - Meetings, 2008-2009, 7 folders (Box 490)
        - Creative Economy Initiative Executive Summary, 2008 (Box 490)
        - Executive Committee, 2007-2009, 9 folders (Box 490)
      - Internet2 Board of Trustees, 2003-2004, 6 folders (Box 490)
        (University Corporation for Advanced Internet Development (UCAID))
      - Lieutenant Governor's Commission on Higher Education and Economic Growth, 2004, 2 folders (Box 491)
      - Meeting of the MIT9 Universities, 2001-2006 (Box 491)
      - President's Council State Universities of Michigan (PCSUM)-Board of Directors Meeting, 2010 (Box 491)
      - Presidents/Chancellors and Commissioners of Six Conferences, 2007 (Box 491)
      - Strategic Economic Investment and Commercialization Board
        - 21st Century Jobs Fund Business Plan Competition, 2008 (Box 491)
        - Conflict of Interest Subcommittee, 2006 (Box 491)
        - Meetings, 2006-2009, 17 folders (Box 491)
        - Meetings, 2009, 4 folders (Box 492)
      - University of Michigan
        - Investment Advisory Committee, 2006-2010, 7 folders (Box 492)
        - Rackham Board of Governors, 2007-2010, 4 folders (Box 492)
        - Sustainability Executive Council, 2010 (Box 492)
      - University Research Corridor, 2009 (Box 492)
    - China Task Force
      The China Task Force sub sub-series builds upon the digital materials from earlier accessions. This sub-subseries contains President Coleman's briefing notebook for her 2005 visit to China to talk with Chinese educational leaders, which includes schedules, talking points, background information on various aspects of China, and copies of signed agreements between the University of Michigan and Chinese universities. Also included is a report on the Michigan-China University Leadership Forum held in May 2006. This two-week forum brought 25 Chinese educational leaders to Ann Arbor for training and discussion on the management of world-class research universities.
      - China Trip Briefing Notebook, 2005, 2 folders (Box 493)
      - Michigan-China University Leadership Forum, 2006 (Box 493)
    - Events
      The Events sub sub-series continues from earlier accessions and consists of files on the Dalai Lama's 2008 visit to the university to give the annual Peter M. Wege Lecture on Sustainability as part of Earth Day activities, as well as materials relating to the 50th anniversary of the Salk polio vaccine in 2005. Files on the Dalai Lama's visit include planning group correspondence and agendas, communications and press releases, and administrative materials on event budget, venue preparation, and security measures. Also documented here is opposition to the university's invitation to the Dalai Lama to give the lecture, including a letter from the Chinese Consul General in Chicago. Materials on the 50th anniversary of the Salk polio vaccine include news articles commemorating discovery of the vaccine, scripts for the anniversary dinner, and agendas, correspondence, notes, and background information from the planning committee.
      - Dalai Lama Visit
        - Buddhism and Art Event, 2008 (Box 493)
        - Budget and Shared Agreements, 2007-2008 (Box 493)
        - Communications/Press Releases, 2007-2008 (Box 493)
        - Contracts for Facilities, 2008 (Box 493)
        - Jewel Heart, Tibet Fund, 1994, 2007-2008 (Box 493)
        - Planning Group, 2007-2008 (Box 493)
        - Q&A and FAQ, 2008 (Box 493)